# **ALI LARA**

alilarag@mail.com • (614) 440-6494 • aliglara @ Linkedin • Austin, TX

#### **SUMMARY**

With my extensive experience in extracting valuable insights from data in both academic and industrial settings, I am a highly skilled professional who excels in fast-paced environments. I confidently utilize my expertise to solve real manufacturing problems through data analysis, always delivering exceptional results. As an adept self-learner and coach, I am committed to enabling team success in all of my endeavors, and I am always striving to push myself to greater heights of achievement.

### **EXPERIENCE**

# Associate Area Manager, Amazon (Austin, TX)

Mar 2023 – present

- Spearheaded a team of 75, devising an efficient inbound workflow that successfully processed over 70,000 packages daily
- Optimized workflow processes, significantly reducing setup and processing time while prioritizing safety
- Strategically assessed labor plans to meet operational goals
- Leveraged real-time manufacturing metrics to adapt team resources effectively, enhancing productivity in 20%
- Monitored performance metrics and proactively identified retraining opportunities for T1-associates, fostering a culture of continuous learning

#### Yard Marshal, Amazon (Columbus, OH)

Dec 2021 - Mar 2023

- Led a 15-member team to develop an efficient loading/unloading system, successfully handling over 40,000 packages daily
- Built an Excel-based tracking tool, dramatically reducing process defects by 75%
- Strategically prioritized commercially crucial deliveries, optimizing business operations
- Ensured comprehensive safety measures for docks, trailers, and delivery vehicles, promoting a secure work environment
- Upheld the accuracy and integrity of the station trailer yard, ensuring efficient logistics operations

### FC Associate, Amazon (Columbus, OH)

Nov 2020 - Dec 2021

- Sought ongoing skill development on under-performing associates to meet production goals
- Outperformed KPIs designed for tracking T1-associates performance: 379 UPH, 500+ average stow rate, which represented being at the 95th percentile
- Classified hazardous residues following federal and local EPA/RCRA standards for handling, disposal, or shipping
- Used technical knowledge to troubleshoot any issues related to damaged packages, processing hazmats, returns, and third-party contractor shipping
- Coached Day-1 and Week-1 associates in standards of work and safety culture

### **Chemical Engineer, MCL Control (Venezuela)**

May 2012 - Sep 2019

- Engineering support for creating mathematical models and simulating gas/oil processess using commercial process simulators
- Shaped machine learning algorithms to develop predictive models and optimize the performance of advanced control algorithms for gas/oil processes
- Assisted researchers team in engineering a standard workflow for implementing non-parametric statistical models in oil/gas processes
- Engineered neural network models in Python/Tensorflow to estimate physical parameters required by process simulations to improve the application performance
- Mentored 10+ junior engineers over one year on using XGBoost and random forest models to optimize the feature selection for machine learning projects
- Gathered information, identified analytical requirements, and developed data-driven based models to translate complex business needs into actionable analytic projects

## Researcher, Universidad Central of Venezuela, Venezuela

Mar 2005 - Nov 2020

• Researched chemical reaction engineering, mathematical modeling, simulation and optimization, process synthesis and design, including economic assessments, process integration, and machine learning techniques for industrial process evaluation

- Lectured in several chemical engineering areas, including thermodynamics, chemical reactor design, numerical methods, industrial process simulation, and statistical modeling
- Proposed a problem-solved learning experience in different subjects following the ABET guidance.
- Coached 200+ chemical engineering undergraduates with regards to academic pathways and toward degree completion and established and provided career counseling for a network of cooperatives, internships, and externships to foster academic to-industry pipeline

## **PROJECTS**

- Design of an industrial plant for solar hydrogen production by water splitting 2020
- Led a research project on sustainable energy solutions using concentrated solar thermal energy to produce hydrogen.
- Compared different hydrogen production technologies, overcoming data limitations, and demonstrating knowledge of the latest developments in the field.
- Used mathematical modeling and simulation to optimize the plant's electric power production, resulting in the selection of alkaline electrolysis as the most efficient technology and contributing to its commercialization.
- Develop a semi-automatic tool for HAZOP nodes detection from industrial process P&IDs 2021
- An assistive tool to perform HAZOP studies based on autoregressive models and machine learning techniques in compliance with design specifications - 2020
- Prediction of turbo-compressors performance degradation using deep learning techniques 2019

### **EDUCATION**

Correlation One - Amazon, Data Analytics BootCamp

DataCamp.com, Python for Data Scientist

Universidad Central of Venezuela, M.Sc. Chemical Engineering

Universidad Central of Venezuela, B.Sc. Chemical Engineering

### SKILLS

- Process modeling: Statistical modeling, Matlab, Hysys
- Data Analysis: Excel, SQL, NoSQL, Tableau
- Machine learning: Python, R, TensorFlow